Guide to the George Bogin Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
George Bogin Papers,
1938-1997
[Bulk Dates: 1953-1988].
Bogin, George, 1920-1988.
4.62 linear feet (11 archives boxes and one oversized musical score).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
6620304
MS#1447
The papers of George Bogin consist primarily of drafts and typescripts of his poetry and translations. Also included is correspondence, biographical material, and a copy of the musical score for Lloyd Ultan’s Pitchipoi, The Children of Drancy, which incorporated Bogin’s poem, “Pitchipoi.”
History
George Bogin, a poet and translator, was born on April 28, 1920 in New York City. A lifelong New Yorker; he was raised in Queens and graduated from Columbia College in 1939. He served in World War II, and ultimately settled in Great Neck on Long Island, where he remained for the rest of his life. He was a passionate supporter of human rights and civil liberties, and was a founder of the Great Neck Peace Forum in the early 1950s. He married Ruth Fleischer (1920-1999), with whom he had two daughters, Nina and Madga Bogin.
He was widely published in literary magazines and anthologies, including The Paris Review, The American Poetry Review, The Nation, Chicago Review, Columbia Forum, New Letters, Massachusetts Review, Kansas Quarterly, and Ploughshares. He also held residencies at the MacDowell Colony, the Virginia Center for the Creative Arts, and the Tyrone Guthrie Center in Annaghmekerrig, Ireland. One of Bogin's poems, “Pitchipoi,” was set to music for orchestra and soloists by Lloyd Ultan in Pitchipoi, The Children of Drancy"(1983). His translation work was primarily from the French, and included Bosquet and Supervielle. He published two books, a translation of Jules Supervielle's works, Selected Poems and Reflections on the Art of Poetry(1985), and his own book of poetry, In a Surf of Strangers (1981).
During the last few years of his life, Bogin struggled with lymphoma, and ultimately succumbed to the disease on October 7, 1988. After his death, Bogin's friends and family established the George Bogin Memorial Award. This is awarded for “a selection of four or five poems that reflects the encounter of the ordinary and the extraordinary, uses language in an original way, and takes a stand against oppression in all its forms.”
Scope and Content
Bogin's papers consist primarily of drafts and typescripts of his poetry and translations, but also include correspondence, biographical materials, and a copy of the musical score for Lloyd Ultan's Pitchipoi, The Children of Drancy, which incorporated Bogin's poem “Pitchipoi.”
The strength of the papers is in their documentation of Bogin's work on poetry and translations. Bogin was well-organized in his creative process; most of his individual drafts are labeled with titles, dates, and a place of composition. Multiple drafts are also numbered in sequence. Most of the drafts are filed by title, although there are a few typescripts for larger collections. Bogin planned to publish a second book, and although there is no typescript, there is a list of the poems meant for this work filed in Box 11. There are a few published items from his time at Columbia University (1938-1939), otherwise, there is no documentation of his early work in his papers.
There is some correspondence related to Bogin's published material, as well as a few items of correspondence with Alain Bosquet, Robert Bly, Malcolm Cowley, and Lloyd Ultan.
Arrangement
This collection has been left in its original physical order, but is intellectually arranged in three series:
Series I. Biographical Materials, 1982-1988, Undated
Series II. Correspondence, 1955, 1982-1997
Series III. Poetry, 1938, 1953-1985
Subseries 1: Original Works, 1938-1939, 1953-1988
Subseries 2: Translations and Other Works, 1938, 1980-1985
Subjects
Drancy (Concentration camp)--Songs and music.; Bogin, George,--1920-1988.; Supervielle, Jules, 1884-1960--Translations into English.; Ultan, Lloyd, 1929-1998.; American poetry--20th century.; Poets, American--20th century.; Vocal duets with orchestra--Scores.; Poetry.; Correspondence
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
This collection was acquired from Magda Bogin in August 2002.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Biographical Materials, 1982-1988, undated
  This series consists of Bogin’s résumé and reading cards, which include information on the use and publication of his poetry. The files also include information on Bogin’s awards, fellowships, interviews, and poetry readings. The “Readings” and “Poetry Prize” files also includes general biographical statements on Bogin.
  - Readings (Material on readings actually performed by Bogin, correspondence, and requests for readings), 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Poets for Peace Advertisement, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Poetry Prize, 1988-1997, (2 Folders); (The George Bogin Memorial Award; includes biographical information) (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Poetry Society of American Awards Ceremony, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Résumé, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Bogin's Poetry Cards for Readings, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1955, 1962-1997
  Most of the correspondence in this series is related to the publication of Bogin’s works or the performance of Pitchipoi, The Children of Drancy. There is also one folder of business correspondence, “Film 66 May,” that is related to H. Bogin & Son, Inc. After 1988, Bogin’s affairs were handled by his widow, Ruth Bogin. There is some additional correspondence filed with Bogin’s poetry files. These files are noted in the container list for Series III: Poetry.
  - Treacle Press Woodbine Press, circa 1975, ("Alone in the House: Poems by George Bogin") (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, General: Open and Closed and Miscellaneous Items, 1980-1986 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Film 66 May, 1962-1966 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Contemporary Reader Copyright, 1955, 1973, (Includes correspondence and the publication with Bogin's poem "Two Poems") (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - UCF (University of Central Florida) Press, 1980, (Mostly related to n a Surf of Strangers) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Paul Janeczko Correspondence (and Other Anthology Correspondence), 1986-1997 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Poetry)--Closed, 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Pitchipoi Files, Permissions and Lloyd Ultan Correspondence, etc., 1983-1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Series III: Poetry, 1938-1939, 1953-1988
  This series consists of drafts, typescripts, and a few copies of items from publications. There is also some correspondence interfiled with Bogin’s poetry files. The container list makes note of files that include correspondence.
  - Subseries 1: Original Works, 1938-1939, 1953-1988
    This subseries includes material related to original works of poetry by George Bogin. This material consists primarily of drafts; there is also a typescript that appears to be for In a Surf of Strangers. Bogin was planning to publish a second full-length book of poetry. Although there is no typescript, there is a handwritten list of poems, apparently made by Ruth Bogin, of poems that were meant to be included in the book.
    Bogin kept highly organized draft files. In most cases, the drafts are numbered, dated, titled, and include the location where he composed the draft. The files were left in their original order.
    One of Bogin’s poems, “Pitchipoi,” was set to music in Pitchipoi, The Children of Drancy by Lloyd Ultan. Drafts of the poem and a copy of the musical score are included in this subseries.
    - Daughter II PPS 201, 1959 February 1-November 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Daughter Rewrite, 1961-1963, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - 50 Poets-Trees, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Facts, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (Also titled "Homage à Magritte")
    - Bartender, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Grandfather's Room, 1958-1959, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Georges L'Oiseleur and René Dova, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Grandmother, 1963, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Great Neck, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hurricane, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - How to Write a Poem, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Home, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      (Also titled "The House")
    - Home Movies, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Strand, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Haircut, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Initiate, 1960, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Jew Remembers, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Pitchipoi, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Poems and Their Burdens, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - A Poem Entitled Untitled, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Pogrom, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Praskovya Feodorovna, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Arterio, 1957-1964, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Rifke, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Singular, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The Snows, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Square du Vert Galant, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Stalemate, 1959-1963, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Store, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Still Life, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Stranger, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Song, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Stieglitz, 1954-1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Suicides, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      (Ernest Hemingway and Hart Crane)
    - A Summer Night on Long Island, 1964, 1973-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "A Sunday at the Beach, 1938", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Abraham, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Alone in the House, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - The Attaché Case, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Arletty-Garance, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - At Sixty-Four, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      (Includes correspondence with Ploughshares)
    - Film--What Does Your Father Do?, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      (Includes copy of "The Nation" in which the poem appeared in 1958 See Also Box 4)
    - Translations, 1956-1957, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Veinte poemas de George Bogin: Selección y traducciones de Magda Bogin y Mathilde Daviu, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Poems for Xeroxing, circa 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - The Mediterranean, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - George Bogin, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      (Poem)
    - Martha Nelson, 1977-1979, 1984, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      (Includes correspondence between Ruth Bogin and Mike Kirkland)
    - This Tree is Mine, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Souvenir, 1972-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Cynic, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Snow, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - The Furniture, 1975, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - The Actor, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - The Graves of My Grandparents, 1974, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Immortality, 1973, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - When Things Run Deep, 1972, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Friends, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Short Poems, 1971, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - The Eisenhower Cubes, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Notes on a Black Sheep, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Jean, 1978-1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      (Jean De Koven)
    - The Beginning of Something, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Snow Drop, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Catalogue, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      (Short notes on various autobiographical episodes)
    - Places, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Innocence, Greed and Envy, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Joe Cooney II, 1978, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Rewrite - Treasure, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Treasure, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - The Towel, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Troopship for France, War II, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Triavil, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - A Twilight, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Three Poems, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Van Diemen Street, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - The Visitor, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Waldo, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - What Does Your Father Do?, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      (See Also Box 3)
    - Whistle, 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - A Night's Work, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - A Young Man Dreams of Hitchhiking, 1976-1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - The 1000-Room Hotel, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - To Be Human, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - At 64, Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
      (Includes a set of "Sample Poems")
    - Repro Art, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 26)
      (Waves)
    - Mr. R., 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Elegy for Joey, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Art, 1975, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - [l'inconnue noyée dans la Siene], Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      (Newspaper clipping of a woman's face)
    - Song of the Corpses, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - The Breast, 1983-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - MacDowell Poetry Notes, 1986 Winter (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sarah, 1978, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ascona, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Fish in Sargent Lake, 1982, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "MacDowell Notes 1983", 1974, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - VCCA Summer, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Untitled, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - The Company of Women, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - [Alone in the House: Poems by George Bogin], 1975 or Later (Box 5, Folder 13)
      (See Also: Box 11.)
    - Notebook Pages, 1983-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      (Poems)
    - Poetry, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Work on 2 Landscapes, 1953 November-1954 March 9, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Landscape, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Early Work on the Lost Hotel and the Canoes, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - The Losers, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Mainguth, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      (Also titled, "Soldier, 1943")
    - Peopled Noon, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Philosophy 148, 1965-1971 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Point of View, 1955-1960 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Nadya, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - The Harbor, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Neighbor, 1957-1960 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Never Died, 1960-1964 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - "1934", 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - On Hearing an Aluminum Disc Again of my Voice in 1938, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Blue, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Bodies, 1975, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Calamine Lotion, 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Cape Cod, 1964-1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Joe Cooney's Story, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Coup, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Cubes, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Decalogue, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - The Delegation to Great Neck, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - A Good Time for Poetry, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Quannacut, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Avenue, 1973-1974, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Snowman, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Uncle, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Fike, 1954-1960 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Detached from "The Beginning of Something," 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - "1920", 1979, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Dust, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Ed Conn, 1974, 1983-1987 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Ashes, 1982-1987 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - On the Death of Rose Fleischer, 1983, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Homage to Diane Arbus, 1985-1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - The Dead Who Walk in My Dreams (Second Version), 1985 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      (See Also: Folder 31)
    - Chicago, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - When the Visitors are Gone, 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Helicoptering, new version, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - The Kiss, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - To Valentine, 1984-1986 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - My Granddaughter Cécilia, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - To Cécilia, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - The Cremation of My Aunt, 1981-1984 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Monsieur Folantin, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Manifestations, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Rain God, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Encounter, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Runaway, 1984, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Bars, 1964, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - The Sigh, 1976-1979 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Forest Hills, 1972-1979 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Rampage, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - The Lightning Cure, 1980, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Lines for Jerome, 1978-1983 (Box 9, Folder 27)
      (On Jerome Mellquist; includes correspondence with Malcolm Cowley)
    - Man, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Snapshot, 1981-1984 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Journey to the Old Camp, 1977, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - The Dead Who Walk in My Dreams, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Which One is the Photograph?, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Sanders a Suicide, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Helicoptering, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Cottontail, 1983-1985 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Déjeuner sur l'Herbe, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - [Poems, Various], Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Working Folder Jacobson Studio, 1988 Spring (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Afternoon and Evening at Torcello, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 13 Ways of Looking at Man, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - My Life on Film, 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Annaghmekerrig, 1981, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - In France, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - [Poems, Various], 1956-1982 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Notes 4, 1978-1985 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - The Three Salesmen, 1984-1987 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Columbia Poetry, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      (Monograph includes Bogin's poem "To Hart Crane")
    - "Special Items" as per Ruth Bogin's Handwritten List, circa 1999 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      (Folder includes correspondence from Robert Bly on Bogin's translation of Supervielle (1986), a few notes on poems, a copy of the 1939 Columbia Review that includes Bogin's poem "Long Island Sound," and a handwritten list of titles meant for inclusion in Bogin's unpublished second book of poems.)
    - Alone in the House: Poems by George Bogin, 1975 or Later (Box 11, Folder 5)
      (See Also: Box 5.)
    - Published Items, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Daughter I PPS 1-200, 1957 December 2-1959 January 31 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Pitchipoi: The Children of Drancy, 1983, (Musical Score) (Box Flat Box 739)
  - Subseries 2: Translations and Other Works, 1938, 1980-1985
    Bogin primarily translated from French and Italian works. His translations of works by both Alain Bosquet and Jules Supervielle were published, and the subseries contains files related to both translation efforts. There is also a file of unpublished Italian translations. Also included is a file of Bogin’s transcriptions of poems from the original notebooks of the poet Samuel B. Greenberg (1938).
    - Translations, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Bosquet Poems, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      (Includes translated poems and correspondence with Alain Bosquet)
    - Typescript for Selected Poems and Reflections on the Art of Poetry by Jules Supervielle, circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Jules Supervielle Photo, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - [Publication notice for Selected Poems...Supervielle], circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Greenberg Poems typed by gb in Philip Horton's apartment September '38 from Hart Crane's transcript of poems in Greenberg's actual notebooks (done in Cambridge, Mass.), 1938 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Traductions de Supervielle Volume I-II, 1980 October 30-1982 July 4, (2 spiral notebooks) (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
    - Le Corps Tragique par Jules Supervielle, (Photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - La Fable du Monde par Jules Supervielle, (Photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Reflections on the Art of Poetry by Supervielle, 1982, Undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Italian Translations, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Selected Poems and Reflections on the Art of Poetry by Jules Supervielle, translated by George Bogin, 1984, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 6-7)